Jacob Burckhardt Collection
Jacob Burckhardt Collection
1842-1968
Burckhardt, Jacob, 1818-1897.
1 linear ft.
German art and cultural historian. Collection contains items both by and about Burckhardt, including correspondence, clippings, printed material, typescripts, photographs, and more.
2745151
Biographical History
Jacob Burckhardt (1818-1897) was a German art and cultural historian. The son of a Protestant clergyman, Burckhardt came from a thriving and respected family who had built their power and political sway over three centuries, many serving as professors and pastors. Burckhardt studied at the University of Basel, focusing on Greek and theology. While attending the University of Berlin, he worked with two professors - Franz Kugler and Leopold von Ranke - who turned his focus to the philological and historical. Burckhardt specialized in the Renaissance and classical periods, and is most known for his work Die Kultur der Renaissance in Italien (1860). He is sometimes credited with developing the field now known as cultural history.
Georg Leyh (1877-1968) was a German librarian, library historian, philosopher, and administrator. He studied philology and history in Munich, Stasbourg, and Tubingen. He began as a library research assistant at the Kaiser Wilhelm Library in Poznan, then worked in univerisity libraries in Gottingen, Konigsberg, Berlin, Halle, Wroclaw, the Prussian Historical Institute in Rome, and the Royal Library in Berlin. From 1914-1917 he served in the First World War. He made many advances to the design of libraries, and is especially known for The Dogma of the Systematic Arrangement.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Jacob Burckhardt Collection consist of correspondence, memorabilia, printed material, and writings. Some material is by Burckhardt but the bulk is about him.
Correspondence contains letters from Burckhardt and a substantial amount of letters to or from Leyh.
Memorabilia contains artwork, photographs, and miscellaneous material.
Printed material contains brochures for books, clippings, dust jackets, and magazines.
Writings contains material by Burckhardt, Leyh, Wolfflin, and others. Some items are handwritten and some are pritned.
Arrangement of the Collection
Correspondence is arranged by sender and chronologically with undated material or empty envelopes at the end. Artwork and miscellaneous memorabilia are arranged chronologically with undated material at the end. Photographs are in no particular order. Printed material is arranged chronologically with undated material at the end. Writings are arranged by author with unidentified material at the end.
Subject and Genre Headings
Historians; Burckhardt, Jacob, 1818-1897.; Wolfflin, Heinrich, 1864-1945.; Leyh, Georg, 1877-1968.; Art historians -- Switzerland.; Art historians -- 19th century.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Brochures.; Photographs.; Typescripts.; Book jackets.; Photocopies.; Magazines (periodicals); Manuscripts for publication.; Art historians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Transfer from Rare Books, 1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - Burckhardt, Jakob, 1875-1887; most are photocopies (Box 1)
  - Burckhardt, Jakob, 1842-1893; transcripts (Box 1)
  - Leyh, Georg, 1906-1962; undated (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Artwork, 1923-1928; undated (Box 1)
  - Photographs, most of Burckhardt (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous, 1912-1965; undated (Box 1)
- Printed material
  - Brochures, 1921-1961; undated; most are advertisements for books about Burckhardt
  - Clippings, 1858-1968; undated; 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Clippings, 1923-1968; undated (Oversize 1)
  - Dust jackets, 1919-1932; undated (Box 1)
  - Dust jackets, 1 item (Oversize 1)
  - Magazines, 1919, 1928
- Writings
  - Burckhardt, Jacob, 1858-1888; letters between Burckhardt and Albert Brenner, Franz Kugler, and Friedrich Nietzche, including some analysis (Box 1)
  - Leyh, Georg, 1953-1962; undated; includes reviews of Burckhardt's writings, From Forty Years of Library Work, and Der Junge Burckhardt. (Box 1)
  - Wolfflin, Heinrich, 1867-1918; biographical material about Burckhardt (Box 1)
  - By others B-K (Box 1)
  - By others M-S (Box 2)
  - By others T-W, unidentified (Box 2)
  - By others, unidentified (Box 2)